A Guide to the Alexandre Rothen papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA193
Rockefeller Archive Center
Alexandre Rothen papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1928-1987, undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rothen, Alexandre
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA193
1 Cubic Feet 2 boxes and 2 volumes
2 boxes and 2 volumes
Biographical/Historical note
Alexandre Rothen, physical chemist at The Rockefeller University (formerly The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research) from 1927-1970. He built one of the first Polariscopes for the study of rotatory dispersion in the ultraviolet range and developed the air-driven centrifuge (originally designed by Pickels of the Rockefeller Foundation). From 1942 he was interested in monomolecular layers and published many papers on chemical interactions at a liquid-solid interface. He built the first ellipsometer with a half shadow device.
Biographical note
1900 Born January 25 Geneva, Switzerland
1924 D. Sc. Chemical Engineering, University of Geneva
1926 Ph. D. Physical Chemistry University of Geneva
1926-1927 Volunteer in P.A.T. Levene laboratory, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York City.
1928-1936 Assistant RIMR. Physical chemist in Levene lab.
1936-1947 Associate in Physical Chemistry RIMR
1947-1966 Associate member and Associate Professor, Rockefeller University
1966 Prof
1970- Professor Emeritus (Home: 1801 Mont-Pélerin) Vaud Switzerland
1987 Died December 12
Scope and Contents note
Biography, Photographs, Bibliography, Collected Reprints.
The papers consist primarily of materials prepared by Alexandre Rothen for press information and include photocopy of news stories 1960-1970. The copies of correspondence and the summaries of experimental work deal mainly with Dr. Rothen's assumption in 1948 (later shown experimentally) that a "specific long-range interaction took place across the membrane between the condensed film of protein immobilized on the slide and antibodies or trypsin molecules", and the violent criticism of this work and the fact that later, the priority of his work did not receive recognition.
Also includes a short biography written by Dr. Rothen.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Date received or inventoried: June 1975; except for: Faculty and Personal Files (Box 2) which was received from Faculty Administration office on March 25, 1988; and folder of figures, graphs, and tables which was received December 1983 from T.P. King.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 R743
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Enzymes; Immunoglobulins; Biochemistry; Trypsin; Chemistry; Life sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medical education; Medical research; Proteins; Biology -- Research; Rothen, Alexandre; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Reprints (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Add to list of publications (after bd. vols, made).
  - Tryptic action across a membrane. Physiological chemistry and physics 11 (1979) 481-489 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Influence of metallic shields on presumably cosmic radiation affecting surfaces of nickel-plated slides used in immunological studies. Physiological chemistry and physics 11 (1979) 193-204 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- MS: Alexandre Rothen, "An Exact Twenty-Four Hour Periodicity in the Superficial Topography of Nickel Plated Glass Slides Presumably Caused by a Solar Radiation of Great Penetration", circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  With handwritten letter to Mrs. [Sonya W.] Mirsky, 15 July 1983.
- Faculty and Personal Files
  - 1928-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1928-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1929, 1958, 1966, 1949, 1970; 5 items (Box 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Emeritus (1970?)
- Figures, graphs, and tables, Oversize
  Separated Materials
  Relocated to map case
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to the oversize nature and potentially brittle condition of the contents of this collection, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
- Collected Reprints, 2 volumes
  Relocated to RAC library 8/9/88